Imagine you're watching a runaway trolley /ˈtrɒlɪ  电车/
barreling /ˈbærəl 桶/ down the tracks
straight towards five workers
who can't escape /ɪˈskeɪp/.
You happen to be standing next to a switch
that will divert /daɪˈvɜːt 使转向/ the trolley /ˈtrɒlɪ  电车/
onto a second track.
Here's the problem.
That track has a worker on it, too,
but just one.
What do you do?
Do you sacrifice one person to save five?
This is the trolley /ˈtrɒlɪ/ problem,
a version of an ethical /ˈɛθɪkəl 伦理的 处方药/ dilemma /dɪˈlemə 困境/ that
philosopher /fɪˈlɒsəfə 哲学家/ Philippa Foot devised /dɪˈvaɪz  n 遗赠，遗赠的财产 v 设计，发明/ in 1967.
It's popular because it forces us
to think about how to choose
when there are no good choices.
Do we pick the action
with the best outcome
or stick to a moral /ˈmɒrəl 道德/ code that prohibits
causing someone's death?
In one survey, about 90% of respondents /rɪˈspɒndənt 回答者；被告/
said that it's okay to flip /flɪp 按（开关）/ the switch,
letting one worker die to save five,
and other studies, including a virtual /ˈvɜːtʃʊəl 实质上的；虚拟的/
reality /rɪˈælɪtɪ/ simulation of the dilemma /dɪˈlemə 困境/,
have found similar results.
These judgments are consistent with the
philosophical /ˌfɪləˈsɒfɪkəl/ principle /ˈprɪnsɪpəl ˈprɪnsəpəl 法则/ of utilitarianism /juːˌtɪlɪˈtɛərɪəˌnɪzəm 功利主义/
which argues /ˈɑːɡjuː 争论/ that
the morally /ˈmɒrəlɪ 道德上/ correct decision
is the one that maximizes /ˈmæksɪˌmaɪz/ well-being
for the greatest number of people.
The five lives outweigh /比…重要/ one,
even if achieving that outcome requires
condemning /kənˈdɛm 谴责；宣判/ someone to death.
But people don't always take
the utilitarian /juːˌtɪlɪˈtɛərɪən 功利主义者/ view,
which we can see by changing
the trolley problem a bit.
This time, you're standing on a bridge
over the track
as the runaway trolley approaches.
Now there's no second track,
but there is a very large man
on the bridge next to you.
If you push him over,
his body will stop the trolley,
saving the five workers,
but he'll die.
To utilitarians /juːˌtɪlɪˈtɛərɪən 功利主义者/,
the decision is exactly the same,
lose one life to save five.
But in this case, only about 10% of people
say that it's OK to throw the man
onto the tracks.
Our instincts /instiŋkt 本能；直觉/ tell us that deliberately /diˈlibəritli 故意地；从容不迫地/
causing someone's death
is different than allowing them to die
as collateral /kɒˈlætərəl 担保品，抵押品 并行的/ damage.
It just feels wrong for reasons
that are hard to explain.
This intersection /ˌɪntəˈsɛkʃən 交叉点/ between ethics /ˈeθɪks 道德规范/
and psychology /saɪˈkɒlədʒɪ 心理学/
is what's so interesting
about the trolley problem.
The dilemma /dɪˈlemə 困境/ in its many variations /ˌvɛərɪˈeɪʃən 不同版本/ reveal /rɪˈviːl 揭示/
that what we think is right or wrong
depends on factors other than
a logical weighing of the pros /prəʊ 赞成者 赞成票/ and cons /kɒn 反对票/.
For example, men are more likely
than women
to say it's okay to push the man
over the bridge.
So are people who watch a comedy clip
before doing the thought experiment.
And in one virtual /ˈvɜːtʃʊəl/ reality study,
people were more willing
to sacrifice men than women.
Researchers have studied
the brain activity
of people thinking through the classic
and bridge versions.
Both scenarios /sɪˈnɑːrɪˌəʊ 情节；剧本；方案/ activate areas of the brain
involved in conscious /ˈkɒnʃəs 意识到的/ decision-making
and emotional responses.
But in the bridge version,
the emotional response is much stronger.
So is activity in an area of the brain
associated with processing
internal conflict.
Why the difference?
One explanation /ˌɛkspləˈneɪʃən 解释/ is that pushing someone
to their death feels more personal,
activating an emotional aversion /əˈvɜːʃən 厌恶；讨厌的人或东西/
to killing another person,
but we feel conflicted because we know
it's still the logical choice.
"Trolleyology" has been criticized by some
philosophers and psychologists.
They argue /ˈɑːɡjuː/ that it doesn't reveal anything
because its premise /ˈprɛmɪs 前提/ is so unrealistic /ˌʌnrɪəˈlɪstɪk/
that study participants
don't take it seriously.
But new technology is making this kind
of ethical /ˈɛθɪkəl/ analysis
more important than ever.
For example, driver-less cars
may have to handle choices
like causing a small accident
to prevent a larger one.
Meanwhile, governments are researching
autonomous /ɔːˈtɒnəməs 自治的/ military /ˈmɪlɪtərɪ/ drones /drəʊn/
that could wind up / 最后落得/ making decisions of
whether they'll risk civilian /sɪˈvɪljən 平民/ casualties /ˈkæʒjʊəltɪ 意外事故；伤亡人员；受害者；急诊室/
to attack a high-value target.
If we want these actions to be ethical /ˈɛθɪkəl/,
we have to decide in advance /ədˈvɑːns ədˈvæns美/
how to value human life
and judge the greater good.
So researchers who study
autonomous /ɔːˈtɒnəməs 自治的/ systems
are collaborating /kəˈlæbəˌreɪt 合作/ with philosophers
to address the complex problem
of programming ethics into machines,
which goes to show that
even hypothetical /ˌhaɪpəˈθɛtɪkəl 假设的/ dilemmas /dɪˈlemə/
can wind up on a collision /kəˈlɪʒən 相撞；冲突/ course
with the real world.